<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title></title>
            </titleStmt>
           <!-- <publicationStmt></publicationStmt> -->
            <!--<sourceDesc></sourceDesc>-->
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <ab><date>In the mid-1960s</date>, <persName>Marshall McLuhan</persName> prophesied
            that electronic media were creating an increasingly interconnected
            global village. Such pronouncements popularized the
            idea that the era of machine-age technology was drawing to a
            close, ushering in <time>a new era of information technology</time>. Sensing
                this shift, <persName>Pontus Hultén </persName> organized a simultaneously nostalgic
            and futuristic exhibition on art and mechanical
            technology at <placeName>the Museum of Modern Art in New York
                (MOMA)</placeName> in <time>1968</time>. The Machine: As Seen at the End of the Mechanical
            Age included work ranging from Leonardo da Vinci’s
            16th-century drawings of flying machines to contemporary
            artist-engineer collaborations selected through a competition
            organized by <orgName>Experiments in Art and Technology, Inc. (E.A.T.).</orgName>
            E.A.T. had emerged out of the enthusiasm generated by <name type="exhibition"> Nine
                evenings: theatre and engineering</name>, a festival of technologically enhanced
                performances that artist <persName>Robert Rauschenberg</persName> and
                engineer <persName>Billy Klüver</persName> organized in New York in <date>October 1966</date>.
            E.A.T. also lent its expertise to engineering a multimedia extravaganza
            designed for <placeName>the Pepsi Pavilion</placeName> at <name type="fair"> the Osaka World’s
                Fair</name> in <date>1970</date>. Simultaneously, the American Pavilion at Osaka
            included an exhibition of collaborative projects between artists
            and industry that were produced under the aegis of the <name type="program">Art
                and Technology (A&amp;T) Program</name> at the <placeName>Los Angeles County
                    Museum of Art.</placeName>
            Ambitious as they were, few of the celebrated artist-engineer
            collaborations of this period focused on the artistic use of information
            technologies, such as computers and telecommunications.
            Taking an important step in that direction, <orgName>Cybernetic
                Serendipity</orgName>, at the <orgName>Institute of Contemporary Art in London</orgName> in
            <date>1968</date>, was thematically centered on the relationship between
            computers and creativity. This show, however, remained focused
            on the materiality of technological apparatuses and their
            products, such as robotic devices and computer graphics.
            Art critic <persName>Jack Burnham</persName> pushed the exploration of the relationship
            between art and information technology to an unprecedented
            point. <date>In 1970</date>, he curated the exhibition <name type ="exhibition">Software,
                Information Technology: Its New Meaning for Art</name>, at the <placeName>Jewish Museum</placeName>
            in New York. This show was the  first major U.S. art-andtechnology
            exhibition that attempted to utilize computers in
            a museum context. Software’s technological ambitions were
            matched by Burnham’s conceptually sophisticated vision, for
            the show drew parallels between the ephemeral programs and protocols of computer software and
            the increasingly “dematerialized”
            forms of experimental art, which
            the critic interpreted, metaphorically,
            as functioning like information
            processing systems. Software
            included works by conceptual artists
            such as <listName>Les Levine, Hans Haacke
                and Joseph Kosuth</listName>, whose art was
            presented beside displays of technology
            including the first public exhibition
            of hypertext (Labyrinth, an
            electronic exhibition catalog designed
            by <persName>Ned Woodman</persName> and <persName>Ted
                Nelson)</persName> and a model of intelligent
            architecture (SEEK, a recon gurable
            environment for gerbils designed by <persName>Nicholas Negroponte</persName>
                and <group>the Architecture Machine Group</group> at <orgName>the Massachusetts
                    Institute of Technology)</orgName>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>